Guide to the Pacific Northwest Labor History Association Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Pacific Northwest Labor History Association records
1947-2015
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
4552
Pacific Northwest Labor History Association
2.19 cubic feet 4 boxes
Records of an organization which sponsors conferences and other events relating to the history of the labor movement in the Pacific Northwest
The Pacific Northwest Labor History Association (PNLHA) is a non-profit association dedicated to preserving the history and heritage of workers in the Pacific Northwest. It considers the “Pacific Northwest” to be British Columbia, Oregon and Washington.
Members of the PNLHA include trade unionists, students, academics, and others who share an interest in the history and heritage of workers in the pacific northwest region. The PNLHA believes the labor movement must know where it’s been to know where it’s going. It depends exclusively on memberships to sustain its activities.
Adapted from the "About" section of the PNLHA website (https://pnlha.wordpress.com/about-2/ ) on 3/16/2016
Organized into 2 accessions.
Accession No. 4552-001, Pacific Northwest Labor History Association records, 1971-1995
Accession No. 4552-002, Pacific Northwest Labor History Association records, 1947-2015
Conference files, including papers presented, correspondence, CD and DVD recordings, photographs, and related materials about projects sponsored by the association (1947-2015); miscellaneous correspondence files (1972-1990), Board of Directors correspondence files (1990-1993). Additional correspondence, minutes, reports, and agendas document the activities of the PNLHA executive board from 1999-2000. Also includes a file of correspondence between George Underwood and the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) dating July 10, 1971 to August 11, 1977.
Some restrictions on access. Contact repository for details.
Ross Rieder Audio and Video Collection (Manuscript Collection 5930)
Underwood, G.$q(George),$d1880-; Beck, Dave,$d1894-1993$vCorrespondence; Handcox, John L.,$d1904-1992$vCorrespondence; Miller, Jack R.$q(Jack Richard),$d1916-1994$vCorrespondence; Pacific Northwest Labor History Association$vCorrespondence; Pacific Northwest Labor History Association$vCongresses; Pacific Northwest Labor History Association$vArchives; Industrial Workers of the World; Industrial Workers of the World$vCorrespondence; Laborers' International Union of North America.$bLocal 348$vCorrespondence; Labor unions$zNorthwest, Pacific; Labor unions$zUnited States$xHistory$y20th century; Labor$zUnited States$xHistory$y20th century; Labor unions$vCongresses; Labor union meetings$zUnited States$xHistory$y20th century; Labor union locals$zUnited States$xHistory$y20th century; Labor union rules$zUnited States$xHistory$y20th century; Rieder, Ross K.; Laborers' International Union of North America.$bLocal 348; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington)
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Washington (State); Oregon; British Columbia
- Pacific Northwest Labor History Association records, 1971-1995; 4552-001; 1.83 cubic feet 3 boxes
  Conference files are arranged chronologically and contain material other than the conference papers. Only the conference papers are listed on the inventory.
  Conference files, including papers presented, correspondence, and related materials about projects sponsored by the association (1972-1995), miscellaneous correspondence files (1972-1990), Board of Directors correspondence files (1990-1993). Also includes a file of correspondence between George Underwood and the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) dating July 10, 1971 to August 11, 1977.
  Open to all users.
  Donated by Pacific Northwest Labor History Association, 8/18/1995
  - Organizational Records
    - General Correspondence (chronological Order), 1972-1990 (Box-folder 1/1-19)
    - Intraorganizational Correspondence (Box-folder 1/20-22)
      - Board Correspondence, 1990-1993
    - Writings
      - “The CIO in Idaho: The 1937 Strikes” - paper by Patricia Snow, 1975 (Box-folder 1/23)
      - “H.I.T. Rebel” Memoirs of Harry Tucker, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1/24)
      - “Voices of Washington State” - series of papers, 1992 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Conferences (incl. Conference Papers)
      - American Historical Association. Pacific Coast Branch Conference, 1992 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Pnlha Annual Conferences (including Conference Papers, Correspondence, Agendas, Photographs, Ephemera, Schedules, Etc.), 1972-1995 (Box-folder 2/1-16)
      - Conference Papers, 1972-1991
        - Collective Bargaining Practices of the St. Paul and Tacoma Lumber Company 1935-37 by Eugene Hooper, 1972 (Box-folder 2/1)
        - A Look at Enumclaw's Past by Wayne Podolak, 1976 (Box-folder 2/2)
        - An abstract for a paper on the Labor Relations of Pope & Talbot, Inc. by Craig Wollner
        - A Bibliography of Washington State Labor, Laboring Classes, Radical, Political and Social Movements by Jonathan Dembo
        - The Ethnic Experience in Western Mining History: An Examination of the Rosenblum Thesis by Gerald Rosenblum, Immigrant Workers: Their Impact on American Radicalism
        - Writing B[ritish].C[olumbia]. Labour History n.a.
        - The IWA: Its Present As History by Jerry Lembcke, 1977 (Box-folder 2/3)
        - Unionization of Agricultural Field Workers on the West Coast by James G. Newbill
        - The CIO and That "Damnable Bickering in the Pacific Northwest, 1937-1941 by Hugh T. Lovin, 1978 (Box-folder 2/4)
        - In Pursuit of the Cooperative Commonwealth: Thoughts on Early Trade Unionism in the Pacific Northwest by Carlos A. Schwantes, 1979 (Box-folder 2/5)
        - Left-Wing Unionism in the Pacific Northwest: A Comparative History of Organized Labor and Socialist Politics in Abstract: Washington and British Columbia, by Carlos Arnaldo Schwantes, 1885-1917
        - Spokane and the Wage Workers' Frontier by Carlos A. Schwantes
        - Al Parkin, Worker, Organizer, Journalist, Teacher by George North, 1980 (Box-folder 2/6)
        - The Coeur d'Alene Mining District and the 'Wobbly' Connection by Stanley S. Phipps
        - Corruption, Factionalism and Inter-Ethnic Conflict in the Birth of a Union by Jack K. Masson and Donald Guimary
        - The Destruction of the Butte Miners' Union A Study of the Socialist Party, the I.W.W., Mining Enterprise, and the State by Jerry W. Calvert, 1981 (Box-folder 2/7)
        - Abstracts: Circumstances of the Death of Ginger Goodwin by Christina J. Nichol
        - The American Way- Anti-Communism in a Longshore Local, 1938-1958 by Mary___?
        - White-Collar Workers and the Class Structure: Changes in the White-Collar Sector of the British Columbia Labour Force and Their Class Implications by David Coburn and Rennie Warburton
        - Responding to Economic Crisis: A Comparison of Anti-Crisis Activity in the Depression and Today by Philip S. Foner, 1983 (Box-folder 2/8)
        - To: Labor Education & Research Center, Eugene by ILWU President James R. Herman
        - Oral History: The Depression Taught Me One Thing.To Be a Union Member by Lucille Johnson McKenzie
        - The Fraser Mills Strike of 1931: Class and Community During the Great Depression by M. Jeanne Meyers Williams
        - The Educator and the Depression by James M. Wallace
        - The Western Federation of Miners in the Coeur d'Alene and Kootenay Region, 1899-1902 by Jeremy Movat, 1984 (Box-folder 2/9)
        - The Congress of Industrial Organizations, the Wagner Act and the Legitimatization of Labor in Northern Idaho's Mining Industry by Stanley S. Phipps, 1985 (Box-folder 2/10)
        - Lumber and Labor; Violence in the Pacific Northwest by Richard M. Brown, 1986 (Box-folder 2/11)
        - Theresa McMahon and the Labor Movement in the in the Northwest, 1919-1937 by Bradley J. Hillis
        - The Last of the Old-Time Bolsheviks by John Thomas
        - Reflections on Ralph Chaplin, the Wobblies, and Organizing In the Save the World Business -- Then and Now by John R. Salter, Jr.
        - Jay Fox: Anarchist of Home by Mary M. Carr
        - A Good Song Is Worth an Even Dozen Sermons: Labour Songs and the Schools by Mark Leier
        - Solidarity and Fragmentation in American Working-Class History, 1870s - 1930s by Melvyn Dubofsky
        - Reorganization of the Pacific Coast Longshoremen, 1929-1933 by Ottilie Markholt, 1988 (Box-folder 2/13)
        - The Ledwich Papers by David Broughton
        - A Gathering Place During Trying Times: the Seattle Worker's College in the Early 1920s by Sarah Sharbach
        - A History of the Oregon Public Employee Collective Bargaining Act by Marcus Widenor
        - Red Baiting and Labor in Washington State by William F. Johnston, 1946-1950
        - Seattle Labor's 1920 Bon Marche Boycott by Dana Frank
        - World War II and the Unraveling of CIO Labor internationalism, 1989 (Box-folder 2/14)
        - Labor and Capital During World War II: The Example of the Boeing Company and IAM District Lodge 751 by John mcCann
        - World War II: The Remaking of the American Working Class by Nelson Lichtenstein
        - Policing Class Relations in the Age of Lumber Production. The Case of Eugene and Lane County, 1897-1960 by Neil Websdale
        - The Tacoma Retail Stores Strike by Ottilie Markholt, 1991 (Box-folder 2/15)
        - Masters Thesis: A Political Press: Policies of the Washington Commonwealth Federation "A Maverick State Plays Politics" by Alice Jane Kling
        - The Life of Terry Pettus: Journalist, Trade Unionist, and Political Activist by Michelle Stillings
        - A History of the Seattle Labor School by Robert Olson
      - PNLHA Annual Conferences (including conference papers, agendas, photographs, ephemera, schedules, etc.) (Box-folder 3/1-4)
        - Conference Papers, 1992-1995
          - Abstract: Uniform Labor Go[l]dfish Bowl Bargaining From, 1934-1957 (Box-folder 3/1)
          - Seattle 1900-1920 From Boomtown, Urban Turbulence, to Restoration by Richard C. Berner, 1992
          - Democracy and Productivity A Brief Historical Perspective by Del Castle
          - How Shall We Remember the Seattle General Strike? By Ottilie Markholt, 1994 (Box-folder 3/3)
          - British Columbia and the Mining West by David Roth and Allen Seager
          - The Wise Use Movement and the Politics of Disinheritance by David A. Mazza, 1995 (Box-folder 3/4)
          - What Jobs in the Woods? Challenge and Transition for the Forest Workforce by Charles Spencer, Flaxen D. L. Conway, and Bob Warren
          - Communities Facing the Ax: the Human and Ecological Consequences of the Narrative of Sustained Yield Forestry by Stan Beyer
          - Ethnicity and Class Issues in the Muckamuck Restaurant First Nations Workers; Trade Union Dispute, Vancouver (1978-1983) by Janet May Nicol
          - Creating a Dialogue Towards Ecounionism by Christine Micklewright
          - Of Time and Terrain in the American West The Industrial Interlude by William G. Robbins
          - Job versus Parks: The Environment and Vancouver's Early Labour Movement by Mark Leier
          - CAW Lower Mainland Environmental Committee Presentation to CAW National Task Force April 5, 1994
          - Class and the Environment, Historically and in the Present by John Bellamy Foster
          - Across Their Backs: Forms of Work Organization and the Politics of Sustainability Learning From the Columbia River Salmon Fisheries by Blaine Vogt
          - Of Time and Terrain in the American The Industrial Interlude by William G. Robbins
          - More Than Mere Survival: Placer Mining in 1930s British Columbia by Lesley Cooper
          - Creating a Dialogue Towards Ecounionism by Christine Micklewright
    - Subject Series
      - Beck, Dave, 1977-84 (Box-folder 3/5)
      - Flathead Community College Foundation (Perry Melton), 1979 (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Handcox, John, 1985 (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Laborers’ International Union of North America. Local 348, 1980 (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Miller, Jack, 1977 (Box-folder 3/9)
      - P-I Strike Commemoration, 1986 (Box-folder 3/10)
      - “Pioneer Alaskeros” Documentary Project, 1986 (Box-folder 3/11)
      - “Seattle 1919” - rock opera by Fuse Music, 1981-88 (Box-folder 3/12)
      - “Sticking to the Union” - oral history project by Jeremy R. Egolf, 1984-85 (Box-folder 3/13)
      - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade - Spanish Civil War Commemoration, 1986 (Box-folder 3/14)
      - Washington Commission for the Humanities Grant, 1987 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - George Underwood
    - Subject Series - Industrial Workers Of The World, 1971-77 (Box-folder 3/16)
- Pacific Northwest Labor History Association records, 1947-2015; 4552-002; .36 cubic feet (1 box)
  Printed programs, photos, CD and DVD recordings, and ephemera document the proceedings of the PNLHA Annual Conference from 1947 to 2015. Correspondence, minutes, reports, and agendas document the activities of the PNLHA executive board from 1999-2000.
  Some restrictions on access. Contact repository for details.
  Ross Rieder, 2016
  Relocated from the Ross Rieder Audio and Video Collection (5930-001), 2016-16-03.
  - Conference Proceedings and Speakers recordings, 1979-2015 (Box 1)
  - Conference programs, photos, ephemera, 1947-1976 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Conference programs, photos, ephemera, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Conference programs, photos, ephemera, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Conference programs, photos, ephemera, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - PNLHA Executive Packets, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 1/5)